A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President, Logistical Services, Office Files of James T. Ivy FA668
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the Vice President, Logistical Services, Office Files of James T. Ivy
1956-1980
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA668
3.5 Cubic Feet
The office files of James T. Ivy document the concluding stages of Ivy's career at Ford Foundation. Though he held various positions throughout his tenure with the Foundation, the files focus on the last two of these positions – Assistant to the Vice President of Administration and Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services – which he held simultaneously from 1974 until he retired from the Foundation in 1980. The files were transferred to the Foundation's Archives on June 25, 1980, and they were formally accessioned in 2004. Series have been reworked, but Ivy's original filing order (reverse chronological) has been retained. Ivy's files included a small number of budget reports, which have been removed from the collection and replaced with cross-reference sheets. These documents are noted in Appendix C and can be found in the Budget Records in the Archives. Additionally, several folders were removed from the Officer-in-Charge, Logistical Services series. These folders contained information on the Contracted Services subset of Building Services. The records' retention period had expired, so the files were discarded. Such contracted work includes Cosentini Associates – consulting engineers for the building's HVAC system and electricity, Restaurant Associates Industries, Inc. – operators of the Foundation's food services, and Reliance Protective Services, Inc. – consultants for the Foundation's security system. Access to the Real Estate series (box 4, folders 8-9, and boxes 5-7) is restricted; the researcher should consult the archivist before viewing the materials in this series. The Archives holds additional sources of information about many subjects covered in Ivy's files. For most of Ivy's tenure as Assistant to the Vice President of Administration and Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services, he worked under the supervision of Arthur D. Trottenberg, Vice President of Administration. Thus, much of the material in the Ivy collection coincides with that which is documented in Trottenberg's files. Since Trottenberg's files are more extensive than Ivy's, the researcher can use them to supplement information as needed. Some topics, for which the Trottenberg collection may be of particular use, include budgets and retrenchment, affirmative action, information services, and real estate.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Arrangement
The office files of James T. Ivy are arranged in five series:
I. Memoranda (1974-1980)
II. Assistant to Vice President of Administration (1965-1980)
III. Officer-in-Charge, Logistical Services (1972-1980)
IV. Subject Files (1969-1979)
V. Real Estate
Scope and Contents
The office files of James T. Ivy consist of 3.5 linear feet (7 archival boxes) of primarily memoranda, reports, charts and tables, and correspondence. Other materials found in the collection include newspaper articles, telegrams, notes, press releases, leases and sales contracts, mortgage papers, insurance policies, maps, blueprints and floor plans, and photographs. The records document the last part of Ivy's career with Ford Foundation, during which he filled two positions simultaneously – Assistant to the Vice President of Administration and Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services – from January 1974 until his retirement from the Foundation in April 1980. The files include a limited number of records from earlier in Ivy's career, spanning the dates 1956-1973.
The files cover a number of topics that reflect some of Ivy's responsibilities in the Division of Administration. Though this collection does not accurately represent the full range of Ivy's responsibilities in these positions, it is particularly rich in documenting a few topics, most notably the Foundation's involvement in the purchase and sale of various real estate properties. In this topic, along with some others, such as retrenchment and affirmative action, the researcher may find this collection to be a useful companion to the Office Files of Arthur D. Trottenberg.
Biographical / Historical
James T. Ivy held a number of different positions throughout his time with Ford Foundation, beginning in 1953. These office files do not document the entirety of his tenure, but rather focus on the positions he held in his final years with the Foundation. Ivy simultaneously served as the Assistant to the Vice President of Administration and the Officer in Charge of Logistical Services from January 1974 through April 1980, when he retired from the Foundation.
Ivy was born March 23, 1919. He studied Economics at Arizona State University in 1939-1941. Following the University, Ivy served the United States Air Force as a Lieutenant Colonel from 1941-1947. Prior to beginning his work with the Ford Foundation, Ivy held the following positions:
1947-1951, U.S. Government, Department of State • China Economic Mission, Regional Director, North China • Economic Cooperation Administration, Regional Director, North China • Joint Commission on Rural Reconstruction, Regional Director, S.W. China • Executive Officer for ECA-JCRR, Special Assistant to Chief of Mission, Taiwan 1951-1952, The Asia Foundation • Head of Student Relations • Acting Vice President of Administration • Representative, Hong Kong
In 1953, Ivy joined the Ford Foundation for the first time. He began with the following positions:
• January 1953, Executive Associate, Division of Overseas Activities • August 1953-April 1954, Assistant Secretary, Office of the Secretary
After this brief introduction, Ivy left the Ford Foundation and continued working for The Asia Foundation for a few more years:
1954-1958, The Asia Foundation • Representative, Hong Kong • Director of Administration, Home Office
Early in 1959, Ivy rejoined the Ford Foundation where he spent the remainder of his career. Upon his return, Ivy held the following positions:
• February 1959, Associate Director of Administration, Office of the Secretary • October 1959, Assistant Representative, South and Southeast Asia – New Delhi, India, Overseas Development • October 1963, Associate Director of Administration, Division of Administration • October 1964, Director of Personnel, Division of Administration • July 1967, Deputy Representative, Middle East and Africa – Kenya, International Division • September 1968, Associate Representative, Middle East and Africa – Egypt, Libya, Sudan, International Division • January 1972, Deputy Representative, Middle East and Africa – Egypt, Libya, Sudan, International Division • January 1974, Assistant to Vice President and Officer-in-Charge, Logistical Services, Division of Administration
James T. Ivy retired from the Ford Foundation on April 30, 1980. He currently resides in California.
Ford Foundation
- Memoranda, 1974 - 1980; I
  Scope and Contents
  The Memoranda series contains inter-office memoranda spanning a variety of topics. Some such topics include budgets, retrenchment, real estate, taxes, building maintenance, dining facilities, acquisition and disposition of Foundation assets, energy consumption, and affirmative action. Since the memoranda are arranged chronologically, the assorted topics are mixed together, making topical research difficult. Moreover, the Memoranda series provides only limited information on most of the topics. Thus, the files in this series may be used to provide the researcher with a rough idea of the collection's contents, and will likely be most useful in conjunction with the other series as a way of filling in missing information.
  Arrangement
  Series I is housed in one archival box. This series consists of Ivy's chronological files. Items within each folder are arranged in reverse chronological order, maintaining original order. The series consists primarily of memoranda.
  - Chronological Files, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Chronological Files, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chronological Files, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Chronological Files, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chronological Files, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chronological Files, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Chronological Files, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Assistant to Vice President of Administration, 1965 - 1980; II
  The Assistant to the Vice President of Administration series contains records from Ivy's work relating specifically to his position of the same name. As Assistant to the Vice President of Administration, Ivy worked for Arthur D. Trottenberg, the Vice President at that time. In this role, Ivy aided in managing the Foundation’s Division of Administration, which, at the time, was comprised of four departments: Comptroller’s Office, Personnel Services, Logistical Services, and Program-Related Investments. The records in this series focus mostly on the former two departments, documenting, for example, salary policy and budget planning. Other personnel information, namely the affirmative action program, as well as more budget materials, relating to retrenchment, can be found in the Subject Files series. Information on the Logistical Services department is documented in the Officer-in-Charge, Logistical Services series. There is no documentation of Program-Related Investments in this collection. For more comprehensive information on the work of the Division of Administration in the 1970s, researchers can refer to the Trottenberg collection.
  Series II is housed in two archival boxes. This series contains Ivy's files from his role in the position of Assistant to the Vice President of Administration. The series covers a number of functions of the Division of Administration, such as budget planning and salary policy. Items within each folder are arranged in reverse chronological order, maintaining original order. The series consists of memoranda, reports, correspondence, charts and tables, newspaper articles, and floor plans.
  - Division of Administration – General Correspondence, 1973 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Division of Administration: A Thumbnail Sketch, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Foundation Headquarters Building, 1976 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Use of Consultants, 1977 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personnel – Delegation of Authority, 1965 - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personnel – Four Day Work Week, 1972 - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Personnel – Salary Policy, 1975 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Personnel – Overseas Compensation, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Field Offices, general correspondence, 1972 - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Budgets FY1975, 1974 September (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Budgets FY1976, 1975 September (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Budgets FY1977, 1976 September (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Officer-in-Charge, Logistical Services, 1972 - 1980; III
  The Officer-in-Charge, Logistical Services series contains records from Ivy's work relating specifically to his position of the same name. In addition to working on various areas of the Division of Administration as the Assistant to the Vice President, Ivy was also specifically the head of Logistical Services. As Officer-in-Charge, he was responsible for two main departments: Information Services* and Building Services. The Information subseries in this collection contains material related to the library, archives, records management for field offices, early computer word processing systems, and the mailroom. The documentation for the Building Services subseries is less extensive, covering the print shop and purchasing services in just a few folders. Most of Ivy's files that fell under the Building Services subseries were records for Contract Services. These files have been discarded due to their expired retention period. Though the Trottenberg collection does not contain much information on Building Services, it does have an entire series dedicated to Information Services that may be useful to the interested researcher.
  *NOTE: The organizational structure of Logistical Services was reworked a few times throughout Ivy's tenure in this position. In the earlier years, the Information Services department was divided into two separate branches, Records Services and the Library. The two were later fused into one department and eventually renamed the umbrella title, Information Services. For a more detailed depiction of the changing structure of Logistical Services, see the Organization Charts record series in box 2.
  Series III is housed in two archival boxes, and is divided into three subseries: General, Information Services, and Building Services. This series contains Ivy's files from his role in the position of Officer-in-Charge of Logistical Services. Items within each folder are arranged in reverse chronological order, maintaining original order. The series consists primarily of memoranda, reports, and charts and tables, but also includes some correspondence, telegrams, articles, and notes.
  - General, A
    The General subseries contains general correspondence, information on budget and cost analysis, as well as materials on the organizational structure of the Logistical Services department.
    - General Correspondence, 1974 - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Organizational Structure, 1973 - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Budgets, cost analysis, 1973 - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Information Services, B
    The Information Services subseries documents various parts of the unit, such as the library, archives, records management, and the mailroom.
    - Information Services – Small Program Actions, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Information Services, personnel, 1974 - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Library, general, 1973 - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Library Advisory Committee, 1976 - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Library, personnel, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Library, subscriptions, 1975 - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Archives, 1972 - 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Records Management, field offices, 1974 - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Computer, word processing system, 1975 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee, foundation mail, 1976 - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Mailroom, general, 1974 - 1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Mailroom, off-hours communication, 1974 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Building Services, C
    The Building Services subseries contains materials on the print shop and the purchasing department.
    - Print Shop, general, 1976 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Purchasing, general, 1974 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Purchasing, personnel, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Subject Files, 1969 - 1979; IV
  The Subject Files series contains the topical subject files, documenting some of the issues and activities with which the Foundation was involved during the 1970s. The lesser documented topics include the Foundation’s involvement with a few grantees, such as the New York Public Library, the Travel Program for Foreign Diplomats, and the United Nations International School. The series is dominated, however, by the topics of affirmative action and retrenchment of the Foundation's expenses. This is a reflection of the importance that Ivy's supervisor, Arthur Trottenberg, attached to these two issues.
  Affirmative action became a significant social movement in the 1970s. To keep with the times, the Foundation fully embraced the new movement in a number of ways. For example, the Foundation restructured its staff in order to move women and minorities from "support" positions into "professional" positions. Ford also sought to hire women and minorities from outside the Foundation, to serve as both Foundation employees and contracted consultants. In addition to exercising affirmative action internally, the Foundation began an external affirmative action program, placing a high priority on selecting grantees whose projects emphasized the realization of equal opportunity for women and minorities. The affirmative action folders in the Subject Files series document the Foundation's creation of, and adherence to, affirmative action policies. For more information on the Foundation's affirmative action programs, researchers can refer to the Trottenberg collection.
  Another significant issue for the Foundation during this period in Ivy’s tenure was the retrenchment of the Foundation’s expenses. Trottenberg was involved extensively with the Foundation's retrenchment program, so it is not surprising that this issue comprises the majority of Ivy's Subject Files series. The latter half of the 1970s was marked by a period of severe reduction of the Foundation's general management costs and program budgets. Originally, the Foundation initiated financial reductions to promote longevity of the Foundation's assets, but the bad economies of 1973 and 1974 compounded the need for retrenchment. Severe budget cuts were required to maintain the Foundation’s stability. Thus, Ford launched a Foundation-wide retrenchment program, which affected all areas of spending – from reducing the size and number of grants awarded to terminating the employment of a number of staff members. The retrenchment folders in the Subject Files series document the Foundation's plans and projections associated with this retrenchment of expenses. For more information on the Foundation's period of retrenchment, researchers can refer to the Trottenberg collection.
  Series IV is housed in two archival boxes. The series consists of a number of topical subject files. The two most significant and widely-covered topics are affirmative action and retrenchment of Foundation expenses. Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic, and items within each folder are arranged in reverse chronological order, maintaining original order. The series consists mainly of memoranda, reports, and charts and tables, but also includes some correspondence, articles, press releases, and notes.
  - Affirmative Action – general correspondence, 1972 - 1974 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Affirmative Action – External Grantees and Organizations, 1972 - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Affirmative Action – Goods and Services, 1972 - 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - New York Public Library, 1974 - 1978 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Retrenchment, general, 1973 - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Retrenchment – General Management, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Retrenchment – Program Management, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Retrenchment – Retrenchment of Management Costs, 1974 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Retrenchment – Special Retrenchment Fund, 1975 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Retrenchment – Retrenchment Reports, 1975 January - February (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Retrenchment – Retrenchment Reports, 1975 March - 1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - St. Louis office, 1973 - 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Travel Program for Foreign Diplomats, 1974 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - United Nations International School, 1969 - 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Real Estate, V
  The Real Estate series contains information on the Foundation’s investments in real estate. The Board of Trustees decided to locate the current Foundation building in the vicinity of the United Nations in hopes that the new building would serve as a starting point for the development of the Turtle Bay area. Shortly after moving to this location in the late 1960s, Ford Foundation purchased a number of properties within a two block "core development area," legally coined the United Nations Development District, which spanned 43 Avenues. The Foundation's ownership of these properties was intended to be temporary; the Foundation planned to hold the properties until a body, such as the United Nations Development Corporation (U.N.D.C.), could carry out a plan for redevelopment. The U.N.D.C.'s redevelopment plan received final approval on April 16, 1970. Thus, in the early 1970s, the City of New York proposed to condemn the properties in the United Nations Development District, transferring them to the U.N.D.C. for public use. This process involved officially selling the properties to the U.N.D.C. The Real Estate series documents the entire process, from the Foundation's initial purchase of the properties to their sale to the U.N.D.C. For more information on the Ford Foundation and the United Nations Development Corporation's joint venture to develop the Turtle Bay area of New York, researchers can refer to the Trottenberg collection.
  Series IIV is housed in four archival boxes. The series documents the Foundation's ownership, rental, and sale of various properties in the vicinity of its New York headquarters. Items within each folder are arranged in reverse chronological order, maintaining original order. The series consists of memoranda, correspondence, reports, newspaper articles, leases and sales contracts, mortgage papers, insurance policies, maps and blueprints, and photos.
  - Correspondence, general, 1967 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - United Nations Development Corporation, 1967 - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - United Nations Development Corporation, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - United Nations Development Corporation, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - United Nations Development Corporation, 1971 - 1972 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - United Nations Development Corporation, 1973 - 1978 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Tudor City, 1968 - 1980 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Acquisition of Properties, 1967 - 1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Building Deeds, 1977 - 1978 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Real Estate Reports, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Leases, Insurance Policies, Surveys, 1956 - 1972 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Insurance, Taxes, and Audits, 1975 - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Tax Calculations, 1977 - 1980 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Real Estate Corporations, 1967 - 1969 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Real Estate Corporations, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Real Estate Corporations, 1971 - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 763 First Avenue/341 East 43rd Street, 1966 - 1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 477 Madison Avenue, 1970 - 1971 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - 303 1/2 East 43rd Street, 1966 - 1978 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - 806 Second Avenue/301 & 303 East 43rd Street, 1966 - 1978 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - 808 Second Avenue, 1966 - 1980 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - 810-812 Second Avenue, 1966 - 1979 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 824 Second Avenue, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - 828-832 Second Avenue, 1967 - 1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - 330-338 East 44th Street, 1967 - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 322-324 East 44th Street, 1967 - 1973 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 765-767 First Avenue, 1967 - 1972 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Appraisals of Foundation-Owned Properties, 1971 - 1972 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Sale of Foundation-Owned Properties, 1976 - 1978 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Appendix A: Staff and Consultant Reports in Collection: Administrative
  This appendix lists staff and consultant administrative reports that can be found within the collection. Report numbers are provided for those reports that can also be found elsewhere in the archives. The list is alphabetical by title.